All right בוקר טוב, boker tov, today's דף daf is ע"ו Ayin
Vav and we continue in the important discussion around the definition, halachic
definition of a פצוע דכא וכרות שפכה. psua daka u'chrut shofcha. And
we looked yesterday and saw that fascinatingly, well we didn't see it
but I told you about how some of these definitions are changed
radically after the time of the גמרא Gemara or interpreted in a
radically narrow way in order to allow people with the men with
these conditions to marry. So תוספות Tosafot first of all dealing with
the issue
about saying that there's a difference between something that has injured or
as opposed to if it's completely removed, maybe it's okay. רב משה
Rav Moshe who basically says that even conditions explicitly mentioned in the
גמרא, Gemara, if we now find out that they do not lead
to infertility, are not a problem because the גמרא Gemara in addition
to describing physical aspects of it assumed that they cause infertility. And
positions of other פוסקים poskim including רב הרצוג Rav Herzog that says
that if a medical procedure was done to deal with a medical
condition, since the medical condition was בידי שמים, b'yedei shamayim, that makes
the whole thing considered בידי שמים b'yedei shamayim and also isn't included.
Now we continue in the גמרא Gemara on the bottom of ע"ה
עמוד ב' Ayin Hey Amud Bet where dealing with certain physical aspects,
situations, and determining whether they fall into that category or not. So
the גמרא Gemara says like this: מיבעיא ליה. mibaya lei.
No
you know, let's do like this: הכי אמר רבינא למרימר הכי אמר
מר זוטרא. hachi amar ravina l'mareimar hachi amar mar zutra.
So it is six lines from the bottom on ע"ה עמוד ב'.
Ayin Hey Amud Bet. הכי אמר מר זוטרא, hachi amar mar zutra,
this is what מר זוטרא Mar Zutra says משמיה דרב פפא, mishmei
d'rav papa, הלכתא hilchata is בין כקומוס בין כמדריק כשירה. bein kekomus
bein kemardik k'shaira.
If the penis was basically cut so that now it is either
like thin and tapered like a quill, so the thickness of it
was made thinner, or whether it is hollowed out like a pipe,
like a drainpipe, either but the piping is still there. Either way
כשירה, k'shaira, it is kosher. That is the so although one of
the ideas is פצוע psua which is like wounded, this is not
presumably not considered a serious enough wound, presumably because as the גמרא
Gemara implied yesterday that it did not lead to infertility or that
was the question whether it would or would not. So איל il
that is כשירה. k'shaira. מי מיבעיא ליה, mi mibaya lei, but here's
my question: למטה מהטרה או
למעלה. l'mata me'hatara o l'mala. When we're talking about these types of
injuries or whatever incisions that were done to it, are we talking
about that it was
done above the corona meaning towards the tip, or below the corona?
And as you know, as I've mentioned the other day, above the
corona even if it's completely severed is okay. So the גמרא Gemara
says, no. פשיטא דלמעלה מהטרה. pshita d'l'mala me'hatara. Clearly we're talking about
above, which means towards the body, not towards the tip.
דאי דאיתא דלמטה מהטרה de'it de'ita d'l'mata me'hatara even if it's completely
severed? So therefore when we're talking about these things and it doesn't
make somebody a פצוע דכא, psua daka, whatever, you know, combination of
פצוע psua and a whatever. פצוע psua okay, it's not one of
these problems that's even talking about from the corona to the body.
Okay. So now the גמרא Gemara says פשיטא דאי דאיתא דלמטה. pshita
de'it de'ita d'l'mata. רבינא, Ravina,
so if that's such an obvious question, so why did he ask
it? לשבושי למרימר הוא דבעי. l'shibushei l'mareimar hu d'bai. He was trying
to just confuse מרימר, Mareimar, which hopefully doesn't literally mean confuse but
he was trying to sort of like test him. Okay. I don't
know, הוא דבעי. hu d'bai. ההוא עובדא דהוה במתא מחסיא, hahu uvda
d'hava b'masia m'chasya,
so there was a case in מתא מחסיא. Masia M'chasya. שפייה מר
בר רב אשי כקומוס ואכשריה. shafyei mar bar rav ashi kekomus v'achsharei.
So מר בר רב אשי Mar Bar Rav Ashi
hold on,
what is it?
Oh, so right. So ah. So what רש"י Rashi says this means
is that
yeah, what רש"י Rashi says this means is that the injury initially
was like the מדריק mardik case but then what he did was
he sort of operated on this guy and made, turned the מדריק
mardik case, the funnel case, into the כקומוס komus case and therefore
made it kosher. Don't ask me. Moving on. Okay. So ההוא עובדא
דהוה בפומבדיתא, hahu uvda d'hava b'pumbedita, now there was a case in
פומבדיתא. Pumbedita. אסתתם גופצא דשכבת זרע, istatim guftza d'shichvat zera, דאפיק במקום
קטנים. d'afik b'makom ktanim.
So the basically the pathway of the semen was stuffed up and
it came out from now I don't really understand it,
it came out from you have two ducts. What? One is for
urine, the other is for semen.
Yeah, so this means what but how did they
know that it came out from the urine?
Yeah, but how did they know? Because it all comes out of
the same orifice in the body. Yeah, so anyway, but Michael is
correct, I just don't know how they knew. Somehow it came through
the passage for the urine. So סבר רב ביבי בר אביי לאכשורי
Savar Rav Bibi bar Abaye l'achshurei so רב ביבי בר אביי Rav
Bibi bar Abaye said, "Okay, he's still kosher, I mean who cares,
the stuff is coming out, what difference does it make? I mean,
so..." אמר רב פפא Amar Rav Papa so said רב פפא, Rav
Papa, "משום דאתו ממולאי" mishum d'asu mimulai
since you come from—רש"י Rashi says this means from a family
of that's bereaved because the גמרא Gemara says that אביי Abaye comes
from בית עלי Beis Eli which is cursed—so אמרת מילי מולייתא. amarta
mili mulyasa.
So you say like a cursed thing, so you say like bad
things. Okay, why?
One minute,
or תוספות Tosafos says maybe it means the name of a place,
but anyway, you say things that are not well thought out. במקום
מבשלה שלא במקום לא מבשלה, Bimkomo mevashelah shelo bimkomo lo mevashelah, when
it comes out through its natural sort of place then it gets
cooked, it gets sort of heated by the body and is able
to cause to inseminate, whereas when it comes from the place from
the urinary tract then the semen will not be able to lead
to fertility, will not be able to inseminate and therefore this person
is infertile. Now of course the funny thing about this is, okay
wonderful, so this guy's infertile, but it's not a physical injury, right?
It says that somehow אסתתם istatam like somehow it was like clogged
up. So are we supposed to infer from this גמרא Gemara that
any type of a physical ailment that leads to infertility or maybe
that leads to I don't know things happening differently physically in the
body. I mean we're not talking about a low sperm
count, but since when is something clogged up in the category of
cut, severed or crushed, right? So it's a little bit bizarre that
even if we concede the point that it leads to infertility, how
is it the physical type of a scenario that the גמרא Gemara
had described? So I don't know the answer to that. So what's
your question?
Could be as well. A, is it because it's crushed? It could
be that it's closed.
Maybe it's closed because it's crushed. Okay, that's possible.
B. So what's so interesting here is there is as I think
a source of male infertility in which the semen is too warm
in the body and it kills the sperm. So here it seems
to be the opposite.
That's a good point, right.
That is true.
So medical factors are so interesting.
Yeah, yeah, that's a very good point.
Another question, we always say if these things happen naturally like a
כרות שפכה kerus shafcha it's okay.
This apparently happened naturally. That's a good point too. Right, how was
it אסתתם? istatam? That's a good point, I hadn't thought about that
but you're right. What does אסתתם istatam mean? Yeah, so unless maybe
again it's the combination of those two, something happened that there was
some physical injury that then led to it, so it wasn't בידי
שמים bidei shamayim and it was some physical injury. Okay, אמר רב
יהודה אמר שמואל. Amar Rav Yehuda amar Shmuel.
So three lines from the top ע"ו עמוד א', Ayin Vav amud
Aleph, said רב יהודה Rav Yehuda in the name of שמואל, Shmuel,
ניקב ונסתם nikav v'nistam כל שהוא. kol shehu. If there was a
hole so that would be your classic, פצוע. patzua. It's like a
cut or a wound and again presumably here we're talking about the
penis, not the testicle. And then it was type of a hole
that would have been a problem like we talked yesterday it has
to be flush, not flush, whatever. But anyway, you have this hole
and then it got filled up. So כל שהוא, kol shehu, how
do you determine whether that's whether that's kosher or פסול? pasul? It's
almost like the discussions you have in ראש השנה Rosh Hashanah about
a hole in the שופר shofar that you fill up. It seriously
reminds me of that. Okay, anyway, okay, so what's the story? So
this is interesting, somebody could be presumably a פצוע דכא patzua daka
and then could be healed from that, right? If the injury heals
itself. Okay, so how do you determine whether it's considered healed or
not? And again with the גמרא's Gemara high focus on the issue
of fertility, but let's take a look. כל שאילו נקרי ונקרא פסול.
Kol she'ilu nikri v'nikra pasul.
If when the person ejaculates, from the word קרי, keri, has a
seminal emission, it would tear, it would reopen, so it's פסול. pasul.
Then it's considered that the hole is still there and therefore he's
invalid. Presumably also because it was about fertility if that's what's going
to happen when he ejaculates, so then that'll impact on the fertility.
ואי לאו V'ee lav and if that does not happen, if it
does not reopen, כשר kasher it's kosher. So הוי בה רבא. Havi
bah Rava. So רבא Rava said, היכא? heicha? Asked the question, where
are we talking about that this hole exists? This is going to
be like what we just said before. אילימא למטה מהעטרה Eilima l'matah
me'ha'atarah
if it's below the corona meaning towards the tip, אפילו נכרת נמי
afilu nichras nami even severed would be okay. אלא בעטרה עצמה. Ela
ba'atarah atzmah. We must be talking about it's in the corona itself.
I don't know why it can't be talking about in the גיד
gid from the corona to the body, I don't know.
איתמר נמי, Isamar nami, it
was also said, אמר רב מרי בר מר אמר מר עוקבא אמר
שמואל. Amar Rav Mari bar Mar amar Mar Ukva amar Shmuel. Maybe
it means even in the corona itself. איתמר נמי אמר רב מרי
בר מר אמר מר עוקבא אמר שמואל, Isamar nami amar Rav Mari
bar Mar amar Mar Ukva amar Shmuel, another statement in the name
of שמואל, Shmuel,
ניקב בעטרה עצמה nikav ba'atarah atzmah so specifically if there's a hole
in the corona itself. I don't know, was he? ונסתם v'nistam and
it was sealed up. כל שאילו נקרי ונקרא פסול. kol she'ilu nikri
v'nikra pasul.
So if when the person has seminal emission it would tear open,
it would reopen, it's invalid, ואי לא כשר, v'ei la kasher, and
if not it's kosher. שלח רבה בר בריה דרבא לרב יוסף.
shelach Rabbah bar brei
d'Rabba l'Rav Yosef. So Rabbah the son of Rabbah sent Rav Yosef.
ילמדנו רבינו, yilmadenu rabbenu, let our master teach us. היכי עבדינן, heichi
avdinan, how would we do this? How would we as the Rabbis
determine whether this thing will reopen at the time when the person
ejaculates? Now why don't you tell the guy like I don't know,
look yourself? But the problem is how what's he supposed to do?
Go and have sex with his wife and then do a post-coital
inspection? Because the whole question is, is he allowed to have sex
with his wife? Is he already a כרות שפכה?
k'rut shofcha? So these what do these make? Do we say we
go לחומרא? l'chumra?
Well okay, but now let's take a look. How do we inspect
to determine? So היכי עבדינן. heichi avdinan. אמר ליה, amar lei, so
Rav Yosef said back, here's what we're going to do. מייתינן נהמה
דשערי חמימי, maytinan nahama d'shari chamimi, you get some hot barley bread,
ומנחינן ליה אבית פוקרי, umanchinan lei a'bei pukrei, and you put it
by his anus, ומקרי, u'mikrei, and that will lead him to ejaculate.
וחזינן ליה, v'chazinan lei, and then we'll inspect him. So אמר אביי,
amar Abaye, so Abaye said, אטו כולי עלמא יעקב אבינו הוו? atu
kuli alma Yaakov Avinu havu? What, you think everybody is as frum
as יעקב? Yaakov? דכתיב ביה כחי וראשית אוני, d'chtiv bei kochi v'reshit
oni,
my strength and the first of my of my of my strength.
Virility, thank you. Meaning that ראובן, Reuven, he describes it as ראובן.
Reuven. So חזל Chazal say what that means is that when ראובן
Reuven was conceived, that was the very first time that
יעקב Yaakov had a seminal emission. He was so frum that he
never had a seminal emission before he actually had sex for the
first time with his wife, with לאה. Leah. שלא ראה קרי מימיו.
shelo ra'ah keri miyamav. So you think everybody else is so frum
that they never had, you know, some type of a seminal emission
outside of the context of sex? Meaning you don't have to do
such an elaborate procedure to cause people to cause men to ejaculate.
You know, most men are a little bit more normal and they
will ejaculate with a little bit less sort of of a you
know yeah, they don't need that degree of stimulation. אלא אמר אביי,
ela amar Abaye, here's what you do. מעברינן קמיה
בגדי צבעונין. ma'avrinan kamay bigdei tivonin. You show them very brightly colored
women's garments and that's, you know, for most people that'll be enough
of a stimulant that it'll cause them to ejaculate. Okay, בגדי צבעונין.
bigdei tivonin.
So אמר רבא amar Rava so Rava said back to him, אטו
כולי עלמא ברזילי הגלעדי הוו? atu kuli alma Barzillai ha-Giladi havu? So
the opposite question. What, you think everybody is such a lech like
ברזילי הגלעדי, Barzillai ha-Giladi, like you know, so who was a classic
person who was like who was you know who was like completely
immersed like the Gemara says שטוף בזימה, shatuf b'zimah, like you know,
immersed in licentiousness. So okay, maybe you don't need as radical as
the barley treatment, but it's not that most people like that'll be
enough, you know? Most people need a little bit more stimulation, men,
you know, in order to cause them to ejaculate.
אלא מחוורתא כדשנינן מעיקרא. ela mechvarta k'dishninan me-ikara. So apparently they couldn't
find some good middle category between colored garments and this drastic medical
procedure, so we go back to the medical procedure. Now what's of
course fascinating about this is that here we are, we are causing
actual ejaculation in order for the purposes of you know for some
type of a medical purpose. The medical purpose for the sake of
a הלכה halakha determination. But you know, why hasn't the Gemara said
like oh we're afraid that the person will have הרהורים, hirhurim, or
what do you mean, what about זרע לבטלה? zera l'vatala? So clearly
a, it indicates that it's not זרע לבטלה zera l'vatala because it's
being done for some you know for a good purpose to you
know medical reasons to determine some halakhic status. What about הרהורים? hirhurim?
Well maybe you could say the barley thing doesn't cause הרהורים, hirhurim,
it's a completely physiological response. But the בגדי צבעונין bigdei tivonin presumably
cause הרהורים, hirhurim, right? So what about that? Anyway, so it clearly
seems that in the right type of a context these things are
allowed. And this is very relevant, as you could imagine, for the
issue of procuring semen from a husband who you know and his
wife are having fertility problems. And sometimes you procure semen from the
husband in order you know not for use with another couple but
for use with him and his wife. And here actually it indicates
that those are you know that that would be that that would
be allowed. Now of course you might ask about like you know
does the specifics of how you do it matter? What if it
comes not naturally but through masturbation? What if it comes through more
explicit types of stimulants than just looking at colored garments? But nevertheless,
it does present an interesting model for those types of questions.
Yes, this סוגיא sugya used indeed for in other words, there's a
lot of discussion about the psychological health to adolescents around the question
of masturbation. Yeah, so here you've got a model for for anything
other than the most salacious or lascivious sort of reasons for the
well-being of the person.
Yeah, so that's yeah it is true that this is part of
that, that's you know that's like a bigger jump but there are
definitely the whole discussion about what constitutes לבטלה l'vatala and therefore how
broadly can we say that something is not לבטלה, l'vatala, you are
correct, you know, yeah, so that's this that's part of that conversation.
Yeah yes, so that's, yet it is true that this is part
of that, that's, you know, this is, that's like a bigger jump,
but there are definitely the whole discussion about what constitutes לבטלה le-vatalah
and therefore how broadly can we say that something is not לבטלה,
le-vatalah, you are correct. You know, yeah, so that's part of this,
that's part of that conversation, that is part of that discussion, yes.
Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara says like this: תנו רבנן, Tanu
Rabbanan, נקוב פסול מפני שהוא שותת. Nikaiv pasul mipnei shehu shoses. If
there's a hole, then again one wonders where exactly it is, does
it go all the way into the, you know, the what do
we call the ducts or something? I mean it's in the penis,
but anyway, here it says it's invalid because it leads to dribbling,
like the semen doesn't come out as a stream. So presumably the
hole has to be in a particular place in order to make
that happen.
We already had a few of these נקוב. nikaiv.
I know, that, no, the משנה Mishnah was talking about the testicles.
Here we're talking about the actual penis. Okay, but we've been speaking
about holes until now, but we haven't been describing exactly where they
are.
נסתם כשר מפני שמוליד. Nistam kasher mipnei shemolid. But if it gets
filled up, then I mean this is basically a restatement of what
we said before except it's in a ברייתא, Baraisa, then it's okay
because then the person actually is able to have kids. וזהו פסול
שחוזר להכשרו. Ve-zehu pasul she-chozer le-hachsheiro. And this is an invalidity, the
person was a כרות שפכה, kerus shofchah, but now he's good because
it healed. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says זהו למעוטי מאי? zehu
le-mautei mai? So what is that excluding? Sounds like some type of
analogous case even after it healed would remain invalid. So למעוטי le-mautei
another place where holes matter, not in שופרת shofereis but other place,
קרום שעלה מחמת מכה בריאה. kerum she-alah machamas makah bi-reiah. If you
have a type of a stab, thank you, right, קרום kerum is
more like I think more like a whatever, close enough. If you
have a scab that grows over a hole in the lung, דאינו
קרום, de-eino kerum, that that's not considered a sufficient enough covering and
healing, and therefore it's considered like the like the lung still has
a hole and therefore it is טרפה. treifah. And that by the
way a whole issue about גלאט, glatt, גלאט glatt means smooth, has
to do with how many of like whether there are scabs in
the lung or not and you know is a scab what type
of a scab might be considered acceptable to be to seal over
a hole or whether by the existence of a scab you assume
there's a hole underneath.
Is an abrasion a scab? Is that what an abrasion is, a
scab?
No, a scab is a thing that covers up over afterwards. An
abrasion is the actual injury. צירכא? Sircha? Yeah, צירכא sircha is a
scab, yes. צירכא Sircha a scab? Yeah I mean the קרום kerum
is a little different, קרום kerum is like a membrane actually, not
a scab. צירכא Sircha is more right, so that's why I was
saying scab wasn't precise, קרום kerum is a membrane, yes.
I don't know about animals, but looking at CT of human lungs,
yes,
everybody in this room would have lots of stuff of junk on
their...
Right that's why, that's why the whole issue about גלאט, glatt, you
never get a totally smooth lung and the question is like how
how much of a of a scab is a problem or not
and when does it start becoming a problem, that's what all the
debate's about. But we'll talk about it when we do חולין, Chullin,
moving on. Okay, so, I know we did חולין. Chullin. Okay, you
have to be... Okay. So, שלח ליה רב אידי בר אבין לאביי.
Shelach
leih
Rav Idi bar Avin le-Abaye. רב אידי בר אבין Rav Idi bar
Avin sent the following inquiry to אביי. Abaye. היכי עבדינן? Heichi avdinan?
How do we... What do we do? Meaning let's say a guy's
got a hole
and we want to get
it to
close
up,
right?
What do we do to sort of make the body, you know,
generate, you know, sort of heal itself and close up that hole?
So מייתינן סערתא, maiseinan se-arta, you bring... you take some barley, okay,
back to the barley. But this is actually a barley kernel, thank
you, וממסרטינן ליה, u-mesartinan leih, and we scratch the area near the
hole because then you're going to get the body to start developing
a scab and healing itself. Okay, so you scratch it and you
basically get some blood to come out. ומייתינן תרבא, u-maiseinan tarba, and
we take some fat, ושייפינן, ve-shaifinan, and we sort of, you know,
rub it into that area, okay, and all of this is going
to cause some type of a scab and some type of a
filling up to come out, you know, for the body to do
to itself. ומייתינן שומשמנא גמלא, u-maiseinan shumshamna gamla,
we get a nice big ant, ומנחתינן ליה... u-menachtinan leih... גמלא gamla
means like big? Yeah, like a camel, camel-sized ant, right? We get
a horsefly, like horsefly we get a camel ant, okay, ומנחתינן ליה,
u-menachtinan leih, and we have it bite the area of the wound,
okay, ופסקינן ליה לרישיה, u-faskinan leih le-reisheih, and then we chop off
its head. Okay, and basically as the head is there, as the
head of the ant is stuck into that place of the body
and as it sort of decomposes, somehow the body will then seal,
use maybe use it as raw material, I don't know, to seal
up the hole.
Okay, so what is the barley used?
The barley is used to scratch. Okay, ודווקא סערתא, ve-davka se-arta, and
only barley. אבל פרזלא, aval parzla, but with... to scratch with iron,
דמיזרף זריף, de-mizraf zarif, no, that actually causes like a you know
that does not cause a scabbing, that causes like an inflammation. Okay,
so actually they knew about, you know, that iron can cause whatever
metal can cause inflammation. Okay, והני מילי קטנא, ve-hani mili katana, that
only works with a small
hole. אבל גדולה, aval gedolah, נתקופה נתקוף, nitkufa nitkof, it'll ultimately peel
away, any this type of thing, you know, it won't do any
good. אמר רבא בר רב הונא... Amar Rava bar Rav Huna... המטיל
מים משני מקומות Hamatil mayim mishnei mekomot if somebody urinates from two
places not exactly sure what this means where else the urine is
coming from. What does your English say? Does it give some explanation
for that?
Appears to have a hole or some other blemish.
Where? Like from somewhere else in the penis other than the other
than the tip of it? Okay.
So okay so you're then when they're saying you know both those
two ducts right the urine track to the seminal
again I guess I want to know how did they know. Okay
anyway urine is come so maybe but maybe you're right maybe somehow
internally it's coming through out the two from the two ducts. That
actually might make most sense since our concern here is with semen
and not with urine. Okay so if the urine is coming from
two places where are we פסול. Pasul. That's פסול. pasul. Again fascinating
but okay it's very nice that there might be something different going
on with this person's body but as we said before about the
other case A why isn't it בידי שמים Bidei Shamayim and B
why is it the physical injury that's being described unless again you
say that this is as a result of some type of physical
injury. Anyway פסול. Pasul. אמר רבא לית הלכתא Amar Rava leit hilcheta
and the הלכה halacha is not לית הלכתא leit hilcheta not like
the son the רבה בר רב הונא Rabbah bar Rav Huna who
just said this that it's not פסול. pasul. Why not I don't
know either because it doesn't cause infertility or for the reasons we
said בידי שמים Bidei Shamayim etc. ולא כאבא V'lo k'abba and neither
do we rule like a statement of his father's. So ברה דאמרן
Bra de'amran the son we said the statement about the urine from
two places we don't rule like that. אבא Abba the father דאמר
רב הונא D'amar Rav Huna says רב הונא Rav Huna נשים המסוללות
זו בזו פסולות Nashim hamisolelot zo b'zo psulot women who like you
know are intertwined one with the other rub against one another seems
clearly to be talking about lesbian sex are פסולות לכהונה Psulot l'kehuna
are invalid for כהונה. kehuna. Now what does that mean they're invalid
for כהונה? kehuna? רש"י Rashi says it means כהן גדול Kohen Gadol
that somehow it's a problem in the concept of like בתולה besulah
right? It's an interesting how הלכה halacha deals with the issue about
lesbian sex since הלכה halacha really only recognizes not here but in
another place תוספות Tosafot quotes it because because you
know there's a parallel in this גמרא Gemara because because you know
הלכה halacha only understands of sex as requiring basically as you know
a penile penetration you know either either either anal or vaginal. So
therefore when you're not when you're dealing with only women you know
it can't הלכתא halachically be considered to be sex. So I mean
if you know and whatever leads to very fascinating issues about you
know women's perspective about
how whatever larger feminist issue here going on here but anyway so
it raises an interesting הלכה'ס halacha's point about what what are you
going to do with this? I mean you can't actually call it
sex so רש"י Rashi understands that okay but maybe it might not
be sex but she's not exactly a בתולה. besulah. Okay so that's
how רש"י Rashi understands what that means. תוספות Tosafot says it's actually
trying to say that פסול pasul for a normal כהן kohen that
it falls into the category of זונה zona which also raises interesting
questions about the idea of the category of זונה zona for type
of sexual behavior that the גמרא Gemara sees as improper but that
again is not technically הלכתא halachically sex.
So that's his statement and the גמרא Gemara says we don't rule
that way. They're not פסולות לכהונה. Psulot l'kehuna. ואפילו לרבי אלעזר V'afilu
l'Rabbi Elazar even according to רבי אלעזר Rabbi Elazar who says פנוי
הבא על פנויה שלא לשם אישות עשאה זונה Panui haba al pnuyah
shelo l'shem ishut asah'ah zona
that any type of improper sexual activity even if it's not being
transgressing necessarily a clear prohibition even if it's just extramarital sex single
man single woman and so on that's enough to constitute an aspect
of זנות. znut. That might be true but התם מילי איש Hatam
mili ish that's when you're dealing with a man and therefore you're
dealing with actually הלכתא halachically defined sex. So what he's saying is
you've got an act of הלכתא halachically defined sex it's just that
it does not it's not clearly transgressing an איסור. issur. Nevertheless it
could still be זנות. znut. Okay but that's when you're dealing with
that. אבל אשה Aval isha when you're dealing with with two women
פריצותא בעלמא Pritzuta b'alma you can't call it הלכתא halachically sex and
therefore you can't make it considered a זנות znut or a non-בתולה
besulah and therefore it's just like licentious behavior you know but it's
not זנות. znut. So this is a fascinating גמרא Gemara as you
can imagine nowadays in particular when we know or with aspects about
LGBT and inclusion and so on and how sort of הלכה halacha
deals with gay men how הלכה halacha deals with gay women etc.
And you know it raises interesting questions on the one hand similar
to other areas like you know we've been dealing with questions about
attitudes towards masturbation and הרהור hirhur and so on where הלכה halacha
usually has less to say to forbid when you're dealing with women
than with men and so on the one hand you could say
okay it's not as restrictive on the other hand you could say
it's not as restrictive because it doesn't give any weight to those
types of things right? It only gives weight to an act of
sex that involves the male genitalia you know and so on. So
it's interesting by the way you could have הלכתא halachic sex with
two men right? That's the biblical prohibition about homosexuality right? So so
you know you need the man to be the firm of הלכתא
halachic sex you need the man for there to be a problem
of זרע לבטלה zera l'vatala you might need the man for there
to be a problem of הרהור. hirhur. So it raises interesting questions
about הלכה halacha which is more lenient when it comes to women
but often because women aren't really on the radar screen.
Good question if a married woman did this would the הלכה'ס halacha's
adultery? Guess not, right?
Correct. Okay, and then the other is maybe we missed this yesterday,
but it was mentioned earlier. What would we rule in terms of
all this? We ruled naturally it's not a problem if this happens?
I mean, what do we rule? I mean, whatever, a lot of
this development is after the גמרא. Gemara. Yes, we certainly rule בידי
שמים bidei shamayim it's not a problem. But the fascinating development, you
weren't here yesterday and I don't know when you came in this
morning but I reviewed it, but, so, but you know, but the
bigger חידוש chiddush is the type of things that רב משה Rav
Moshe and רב הרצוג Rav Herzog says. That things that result from
a natural condition even if then a medical procedure was done is
what רב הרצוג Rav Herzog says or what רב משה Rav Moshe
says is like, you know, anything that we know doesn't cause infertility
even if it's in the categories of the גמרא Gemara would actually
not be a problem. Those are like, a lot of major קולות
kulot that develop after the גמרא. Gemara.
I have one last question. Can you make a woman a סוטה
sotah by saying you can't be מתייחד mityached with this woman?
No. No, but there is interesting questions how הלכה halacha deals with
that. Okay, let's take a look. פצוע דכא Patzua Daka
וכרות שפכה. u'Kerut Shafcha. Now that we've got through that fun גמרא
Gemara about describing the physical condition itself, let's talk about הלכתי halachic
aspect.
Man who's in this category of פצוע דכא כרות שפכה, Patzua Daka
Kerut Shafcha, מותרים בגיורת ומשוחררת, muttarim be'giyoret u'meshuchreret, can marry a woman
who is not originally who is not born Jewish, a woman who
converted or who was a freed slave, so not born Jewish. דאינו
אסור אלא מלבוא בקהל, de'eino assur ella m'lavo b'kahal, the whole איסור
issur is to marry into the community, which means naturally born Jews.
Again, it's nice to have these leniencies, but I always find it
very challenging because the whole idea of a convert is כגר כאזרח,
k'ger k'ezrach, and then when there are retained areas in which a
גר ger is not considered to be as like in the primary
sort of categorization. Like we heard a גמרא Gemara earlier about טומאת
יולדת tum'at yoledet that you needed an extra word to say it
also applies to a גיורת. giyoret. Anyway, that's going to be a
recurring theme here, that the גרים gerim and משוחררים meshuchrarim are not
considered in the primary קהל. kahal. שנאמר לא יבא פצוע דכא וכרות
שפכה בקהל ה׳. Shene'emar lo yavo patzua daka u'kerut shafcha b'kehal Hashem.
They cannot come into the קהל kahal and so there's the assumption
that therefore a גיורת giyoret who is not born Jewish is not
considered in that category. Okay, so that's
the leniency. So בעי מיניה מרב ששת, ba'ei minei me'Rav Sheshet, they
asked רב ששת, Rav Sheshet, פצוע דכא כהן מהו בגיורת ומשוחררת? Patzua
Daka Kohen mahu b'giyoret u'meshuchreret? Okay, now we've already learned from an
earlier משנה, Mishnah, you might remember, this is how we got onto
this category, that a פצוע דכא כהן Patzua Daka Kohen can eat
תרומה. terumah. The fact that he's a פצוע דכא patzua daka doesn't
affect his ability, he's still considered a כהן. Kohen. Can he do
the עבודה? avodah? Probably not, he might be a בעל מום, ba'al
mum, but he can eat תרומה. terumah. He's just קדושת כהן. kedushat
Kohen. So if he still has קדושת כהן, kedushat Kohen, why would
he be able to marry a גיורת? giyoret? So the point is,
yes, for תרומה terumah he has his קדושת כהן, kedushat Kohen, but
since when it comes to issues of marriage he's excluded from marrying
within the קהל, kahal, maybe therefore that should open up the opportunities
for him to marry the types of people he's normally restricted against.
Okay, so it's a fascinating question. Within the, we're not saying he
totally doesn't have his קדושה. kedusha. Since when would a physical injury
stop him from having קדושת כהונה? kedushat kehuna? But what it does
is it takes him out of certain marriage categories of the marriage
of קהל, kahal, maybe that opens up for him all the other
opportunities.
Okay, but they didn't say let's say a גרושה, gerusha, so then
is that?
Yeah, because a גרושה gerusha would be somebody that he can't marry
even as a פצוע דכא. patzua daka. But the women that he's
allowed to now marry as a פצוע דכא, patzua daka, the women
that are now, you know, now of
course normally, right, right, right. So, right, good clarification.
מהו? mahu? Okay, בקדושתיה קאי, bikdushtei ka'ei, he still retains his כהונה
kehuna restrictions of marriage, his קדושה, kedusha, ואסור, v'assur, and he's forbidden.
או דילמא לאו בקדושתיה קאי ושרי? O dilma lav bikdushtei ka'ei v'shari?
Or maybe, as Michael properly clarified, for the women that now he
is restricted to marry, he can't marry, you know, with the people
that are considered in the קהל, kahal, he can marry people that
are specifically identified as outside the קהל. kahal. That's also the point,
Michael, which is that a גרושה gerusha is not outside the קהל,
kahal, right? A woman is identified as outside of the קהל, kahal,
so maybe things he's restricted against the קהל, kahal, maybe he's given,
you know, he's now free to marry anybody who's outside that category
and these types of restrictions of marriage would not apply.
Okay, ואם בקדושתיה v'im bikdushtei fine, ושרי. v'shari. אמר ליה רב ששת
תניתוה. Amar lei Rav Sheshet tanituha. רב ששת Rav Sheshet said we
taught it. I mean, you understand the problem if you say that
he's אסור assur is then he has nobody left to marry. Right.
So anyway, so you can see the little letter here, the רמב״ם
Rambam at least, you know, that we actually פסקן pasken that he
can marry a גיורת. giyoret. So it actually does open that up.
Okay.
What's the further restriction on a כהן גדול? Kohen Gadol? That בתולה
betulah and not an אלמנה.
almanah. אמר ליה רב ששת תניתוה. Amar lei Rav Sheshet tanituha. רב
ששת Rav Sheshet said we taught it. פצוע דכא ישראל מותר בנתינה.
Patzua Daka Yisrael muttar b'netina. A פצוע דכא ישראל Patzua Daka Yisrael
can marry a נתינה. netina. Now a נתינה netina is somebody who
is from the גבעונים, Givonim, from one of the original sort of
Canaanite nations who then converted, they tricked יהושע Yehoshua and they converted.
Okay, so ואי סלקא דעתך בקדושתיה קאי, v'i salka da'atach bikdushtei ka'ei,
if being a פצוע דכא patzua daka now we're going to make
an analogy to what the story is by ישראל, Yisrael, because the
same way a כהן Kohen can't marry a גיורת, giyoret, a ישראל
Yisrael can't marry somebody from the שבעה עממים shiva amamim and here
once he's a פצוע דכא. patzua daka. And now we're going to
make an analogy to what's שרי *sharei* by ישראל Yisrael *Yisrael* because
the same way a כהן kohen *Kohen* can't marry a גיורת *giyoret*,
ישראל *Yisrael* can't marry somebody from the שבעה עממים *shiva amamim*. And
here once he's a פשיטא דקאי *pshita deka'ei*, he's allowed to. ואי
סלקא דעתך דקדושתייהו קאי *V'ee salka daitach dekedushataihu ka'ei* if he retains
his קדושה *kedusha*, איכא לא תתחתן בם lo titchaten bam *ika lo
tischatein bam*, it should be you're not allowed to marry somebody from
the שבעה עממים *shivsa amamim*. So it shows once somebody's a פצוע
דכא ptzua daka. *ptzuah daka* and excluded from the קהל kahal. *kahal*,
other people who are not in the קהל kahal *kahal* but would
be allowed to be married and restrictions would go off for them.
So אמר רבא *Amar Rava* אתו *atu* one minute, התם hatam משום
קדושה ולא קדושה הוא *hasam mishum kedusha v'lo kedusha hu*? Is the
reason you don't marry the נתינים Netinim *Nesinim* because of a sense
of like yes קדושה *kedusha* or not קדושה *kedusha*? דילמא מוליד בן
ואזיל ופלח לעבודת כוכבים *Dilma molid ben v'azil u'falach l'avodas kochavim*. Let's,
you have to sort of hear this whole thing through to understand
it. Maybe the concern is right לא תתחתן בם lo titchaten bam,
*lo tischatein bam*? Why? Because בתך לא תתן לבנו ובתו לא תקח
לבנך *bit-cha lo titein livno uvito lo tikach livnecha*, you know, כי
יסיר את בנך מאחרי *ki yasir es bincha me'acharai*. So it's all
a concern about having kids and leading after עבודה זרה *avoda zara*.
Now who cares? Like לא דרשינן טעמא דקרא *lo darshinan ta'ama de'kra*.
You know, whatever. You're not supposed to marry שבעה עממים *shiva amamim*.
No, it matters because of the second stage, the rabbinic stage. So
let's take a look. והני מילי בישותן עובדי כוכבים *V'hani milei b'yoshan
ovdei kochavim*. So biblically it's forbidden to marry the שבעה עממים *shiva
amamim* while they're still non-Jews. כי מיגיירי *Ki migyari* but משרא שרי
*mishra sharei* or as a ישראל *Yisrael* when they convert then they're
permitted. ורבנן הוא דגזרו בהו *V'rabbanan hu d'gazru behu*. Now the idea
that you can't marry שבעה עממים *shiva amamim* even after they converted
is rabbinic. וכי גזרו בהו רבנן *V'chi gazru behu Rabbanan* when did
the Rabbis say don't marry them after they've converted? בהנך דבני אולודי
*B'haneich d'vnei oulodei*, only by people that could have kids because since
they understood that that was what was behind the biblical מצוה mitzvah?
*mitzvah*, when they said we don't want you marrying שבעה עממים *shiva
amamim* even after conversion, it's when kids were in the equation. אבל
האי דלאו בר אולודי לא גזרו ביה רבנן *Aval hai d'lav bar
oulodei lo gazru bei Rabbanan*. But somebody who's a כרות שפכה k'rut
shofcha, *kruss shofcha*, פצוע דכא ptzua daka, *ptzuah daka*, who can't have
kids, it doesn't fall into the rabbinic category. So that's a very
elaborate explanation but basically what he says is you can't prove anything
there. There we're dealing with a rabbinic restriction. We're not dealing with
a biblical one. We're dealing with somebody that biblically is permissible, it's
because they converted, the only problem is rabbinic. So fine, we'll allow
it for somebody who is a פצוע דכא ptzua daka *ptzuah daka*.
Okay, because we're not so concerned anyway they're not going to have
kids anyway, what's the big deal? Okay, but that's rabbinic. You can't
use that to prove the issue of a כהן Kohen. *Kohen* by
גיורת *giyoret*. Okay, which is actually interesting because there's some debate whether
גיורת *giyoret* is biblical or rabbinic or not. Anyway, yes.
So this is obviously on the side that you're allowed to make
peace with them, because right there are two sides to this, right?
You gotta kill everybody, but you said you gotta kill...
Yeah, we're not dealing with the making peace, it doesn't matter. This
person, you know, we're no longer at war with them, whatever. We're
not dealing with what יהושע *Yehoshua* did. Okay, so now the גמרא
Gemara *Gemara* says like this. אלא Ela, מעתה *Ella me'ata*, so you
can't prove anything from that. אלא מעתה *Ella me'ata* ממזר mamzer *mamzer*
דבר אולודי *de'bar oulodei* הכא נמי דאסור *hacha nami d'assur*? Ah, you
say ah the whole thing is rabbinic, we're going to allow it
by the נתינים Netinim. *Nesinim* because he can't have kids. So ממזר
mamzer *mamzer* can have kids, we should forbid him to marry a
נתין nesin. *Nasin*. והתנן *V'hasnan* we learned a משנה Mishna *Mishnah*,
it should actually be or עלמא *alma* okay, והתנן *V'hasnan* ממזרים ונתינים
מותרים לבוא זה בזה *mamzerim u'nesinim mutarim lavo zeh b'zeh*, that a
ממזר mamzer *mamzer* can marry a נתין nesin *Nasin*. So obviously it
cannot be based on whether you can have kids. אלא *Ella* fine,
כי גזרו רבנן בכשרים, בפסולים לא גזרו *ki gazru Rabbanan b'ksherim, b'psulim
lo gazru*. Fine, whatever. So the Rabbis said they fine but it's
still rabbinic. So give a different reason. They don't want people marrying
the נתינים Netinim *Nesinim*, but if somebody anyway is פסול pasul *pasul*
maybe you could also say again like a little affirmative action or
whatever, you know, somebody is פסול passul, *pasul* so they don't have
any many too many options anyway, so they let them marry the
נתינים Netinim. *Nesinim*. Fine, but bottom line is the story of נתינים
Netinim *Nesinim* is rabbinic and therefore whatever we do to be more
lenient by נתינים *Nesinim* doesn't prove anything by the case of גיורת
*giyoret*. Okay, that's the basic answer. הדר אמר רבא *Hadar amar Rava*,
then רבא *Rava* said, לאו lav מילתא היא דאמרי *lav milsa hi
d'amri*. You know what? It wasn't right what I said that I
framed the whole thing as rabbinic and therefore said it wasn't relevant.
Why? Because I said that biblically marrying שבעה עממים *shiva amamim* was
when they were non-Jews and rabbinically it extends even when they even
when they convert. It's not true. Biblically we're talking that it's forbidden
even when they convert. How do I know that even biblically it's
אסור assur *assur* when they convert? ביושבן עובדי כוכבים לית להו חתנות
*B'yoshvan ovdei kochavim leis lehu chasnus* because when they're still non-Jews it
wouldn't say לא תתחתן בם *lo tischatein bam*. Not sorry, if I
say don't have sex with them, but it wouldn't say don't marry
them. Okay, their marriage wouldn't be binding.
So נתגיירו אית להו חתנות *nisgyaru is lehu chasnus*. Only when they
convert. So clearly the תורה Torah, *Torah* is saying don't marry them
even after they convert and nevertheless we allow a פצוע דכא ptzua
daka *ptzuah daka* and a ממזר mamzer *mamzer* to marry them. So
you see that once פצוע דכא ptzua daka *ptzuah daka* and ממזר
mamzer? *mamzer* are excluded from marrying קהל kahal ה׳ *kahal Hashem*, it
opens up other people that are non-קהל ה׳ *kahal Hashem* that might
have other problems. But once they're excluded from קהל ה׳ *kahal Hashem*,
these become legitimate and acceptable. So therefore the same is true by
a כהן Kohen *Kohen*, that even though there you're not talking even
there he has a special קדושת כהונה *kedushas kehuna*, nevertheless once he's
excluded from קהל ה׳ *kahal Hashem*, these others people open up. Okay,
so now the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says like this. מתיב רב יוסף
*Masiv Rav Yosef*, so רב יוסף *Rav Yosef* asked them this, how
could you say that the תורה Torah. *Torah* wouldn't say לא תתחתן
*lo sischatein* unless it was talking about after conversion? But it says
ויתחתן שלמה Shlomo את בת פרעה bat Paro, מלך מצרים Mitzrim. *Vayischatein
Shlomo es bas Paroh melech
Mitzrayim*, Shlomo married בת פרעה bat Paro.
*bas Paroh*. Wow, and she didn't convert? So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*
says דיגיירה *digayara* alright, he converted her. And Don't we know that
they didn't accept converts in the time of דוד David, and שלמה
Shlomo because it was assumed to be for ulterior motives? So the
גמרא Gemara says right, מיהוי טעמא משום שולחן מלכים. mihavai ta'ama mishum
shulchan melachim. The only reason they didn't accept converts was they thought
that people were doing it to be part of the king's table,
meaning because that's when the Jews had it good, so they were
suspicious of ulterior motives. הא לא צריכה לה, Ha lo tzricha lah,
it says it should be lah, not lei. Anyway, anyway by בת
פרעה, bat Paroh, she didn't need שולחן מלכים, shulchan melachim, she came
from שולחן מלכים, shulchan melachim, so therefore she was converted. Okay. So
the גמרא Gemara says וטיפוק ליה דעמיצרית ראשונה היא. v'teipuk lei d'amitzrit
rishona hi. גמרא Gemara says I still don't get how שלמה Shlomo
was allowed to do it, that's how תוספות Tosafot understands the question.
She's a מצרית. Mitzrit. And it says לא יבוא, lo yavo, you
know, לא יבוא מצרי, lo yavo Mitzri, what is it? מה הפסוק?
mah hapasuk? לא יבוא lo yavo מה, mah, עד דור... ad dor...
No, דור שלישי יבוא להם בקהל השם. dor shelishi yavo lahem bikhal
Hashem. לא יבוא... lo yavo... right, לא תתעב מצרי כי אחיך הוא,
lo tita'ev
Mitzri
ki achicha hu, לא תתעב מצרי כי גר היית בארצו, lo tita'ev
Mitzri ki ger hayita b'artzo, then I think for sure בנים אשר
יולדו להם
דור שלישי יבוא להם בקהל
השם.
banim asher yivaldu lahem דור שלישי יבוא להם בקהל השם dor shelishi
yavo lahem bikhal Hashem.
It's not even a לא תעשה, lo ta'aseh, it's just an עשה.
aseh. Yeah, you're probably right,
it's a לאו הבא מכלל עשה.
lav haba
miklal aseh. Okay, anyway, so the גמרא Gemara says וטיפוק ליה דעמיצרית
ראשונה היא. v'teipuk lei d'amitzrit rishona hi. She's a מצרית Mitzrit of
the first generation and only third generation is allowed.
When we say first generation, we mean like if a מצרי Mitzri
converts...
If a מצרי Mitzri converts, their grandkids can marry in.
Right, so he's not taking it to mean that like, you know,
מצרי ראשונה Mitzri rishonah at the time of...
No, from the time of conversion. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says
וכי תימא הני אזלו לעלמא והני אחריני נינהו. v'ki teima hanei azlu
l'alma v'hanei achrinei ninhu. Ah, maybe the people currently living in Egypt
are not the מצרי Mitzri from the תורה, which actually we know
to be the case you know right now certainly. They're not the
original מצרים. Mitzrim. But anyway, so maybe the מצרית Mitzrit that שלמה
Shlomo. married was not the מצרית Mitzrit from the time of the
תורה.
And that would have even been before סנחריב Sancheirev came and was
מבבל את האומות, mevabel et ha'umot, that was the time of שלמה.
Shlomo, גמרא Gemara says no, they are still the same
מצרים. Mitzrim. ותניא, v'tanya, we taught in a ברייתא, Baraita, אמר רבי
יהודה, amar Rabbi Yehuda, said רבי יהודה, Rabbi Yehuda, מנימין גר מצרי
היה לי חבר Minyamin ger Mitzri haya li chaver מתלמידי רבי עקיבא.
mitalmidei Rabbi Akiva. I had a colleague מנימין Minyamin who was a
מצרי Mitzri convert from the students of רבי עקיבא. Rabbi Akiva. ואמר,
v'amar, and he said to me, אני מצרי ראשון, ani Mitzri rishon,
I am a first-generation convert of a מצרי, Mitzri, ונשאתי מצרית ראשונה,
v'nasati Mitzrit rishona, and I married a woman who converted as a
מצרית Mitzris first generation.
אשי לבני מצרית שניה, asi livni Mitzrit shniya, I will have my
son marry a second-generation מצרית, Mitzrit,
כדי שבן בני יהיה ראוי לבוא בקהל, k'dei sheben bni yihiyeh ra'uy
lavo bakahal, so my grandson will be a third generation and permitted.
So there you see it's number of generations from the time of
conversion. It's also very significant that he says I'll have my son
marry a second generation because the הלכה halacha here is הולכין אחר
הפסול, holchin achar hapsul, that if you had a first generation married
a second generation, wouldn't matter who's the male who's the female, the
child is considered second generation. Okay, you always go by the more
problematic status. So you would need a second generation and second generation
to produce a third. You could also have a second generation marry
a third generation produce a third, but you got the idea. Anyway,
the point being like the point being that he's considering himself to
be a halachic מצרי Mitzri even though that was way after the
case of שלמה, Shlomo? that was even after סנחריב Sancheirev came and
was מבבל את האומות. mevabel et ha'umot. Now, so you see we're
dealing with real מצרים. Mitzrim. I'll tell you what תוספות Tosafot says
about that in a minute, but let's just see what the גמרא's
Gemara answer is. אמר רב פפא, Amar Rav Papa, said רב פפא,
Rav Papa, אנן משלמה ליכא דלסוף? anan miShlomo leika d'lisof? We're going
to start worrying about שלמה? Shlomo שלמה לא נסיב מידי. Shlomo lo
nasiv midi. Now you would have said maybe שלמה Shlomo was transgressing,
but that's not what it said. שלמה Shlomo didn't really get married
to them. Okay, לא נסיב מידי. lo nasiv midi. So the גמרא
Gemara says he slept with them, had sex with them, he didn't
really marry בת פרעה. So the גמרא Gemara says דכתיב ביה d'chtiv
bei מן הגויים... min hagoyim... so דכתיב ביה d'chtiv bei it says
by שלמה Shlomo מן הגויים אשר אמר השם
אל בני ישראל לא תבואו בהם,
min hagoyim asher amar Hashem el
bnei Yisrael
lo tavou bahem,
we'll get there, מן הגויים אשר אמר השם אל בני ישראל לא
תבואו בהם, min hagoyim asher amar Hashem el bnei Yisrael lo tavou
bahem, from the nations that God said do not enter among them,
והם לא יבואו בכם, v'hem lo yavo'u bachem, and they shouldn't come
among you, meaning don't intermarry, אכן יטו את לבבכם, achen yatu et
l'vavchem, they will surely turn your heart astray, אחרי אלוהיהם acharei eloheihem
after their gods, בהם דבק שלמה לאהבה, bahem davak Shlomo l'ahava, unto
them שלמה Shlomo cleaved for love. So it says ah, you see
it says he cleaved for love of them. He lusted after them,
he loved them, he didn't marry them. Okay. So the גמרא's Gemara
better now.
אלא קשיא, Ela kashya, right.
אלא, first of all, תוספות Tosafot says an interesting issue that we
have sort of alluded, you know, mentioned a number of times but
have not concretized because it's not always explicit, which is the relationship
of these איסורים isurim that are about marriage to issues about sex.
Right, like for example כרות שפכה, k'rut shofcha you know if you
remember the משנה Mishnah said if the condition happened after marriage, the
woman doesn't become פסול pasul. until she has sex with him, right?
So clearly sex is part of the prohibition, right? Let's say there's
a כרות שפכה krut shofcha that has sex with a woman not
in the context of marriage. Let's say it's just about sex. Let's
say a כהן Kohen. has sex with a גרושה grusha not in
the context of marriage, right? Is it about marriage and sex, is
it just about marriage, is it whatever? So here for example the
גמרא Gemara says by the מצרי Mitzri problem, oh, he wasn't married,
that makes it okay. Right? So A, that does interest halachically, I
mean we would have said also, like A, is it morally okay,
is it proper? B, right, who says that שלמה Shlomo? was actually
following that מצוה? But it is fascinating that the גמרא Gemara makes
it seem that halachically at least by the issue of the מצרי,
Mitzri, right, it is לבוא בקהל השם lavo be'kahal Hashem requires the
issue of marriage. However, from the משנה Mishnah we saw about the
כרות שפכה it also had the aspect of having sex in order
for the woman to become פסול, pasul. right? So it's interesting the
combination of those two. Anyway, that's one minute, that's the גמרא's Gemara
answer. The גמרא Gemara. says that he didn't actually marry them. So
the גמרא Gemara says, אה, אלא קשיא ויתחתן, Ah, ella kashya vayischaten,
but it says that he married. Okay. מתוך אהבה יתירה שאהב, Mitoch
ahava yeseira she'ahava, because of the great love that he loved בת
פרעה, מעלה עליו כאילו יתחתן בה, ma'alah alav kekeilu yischaten bah, it
was as if they were married, it was a civil law marriage,
it was like a common law marriage, you know, they were so
they were so bound together, they were soulmates, but they weren't technically
married. דוב, Dov, you had a question?
Just on the grammar: ליכא leiko and נצי, natsi, what's the לשון
lashon of ליכא? leiko?
Should we get up and ask a question from שלמה? Shlomo ליכא
leiko and מצי. mitsai. Yeah, exactly. Right, right.
And נביא Navi does?
Right.
Oh, what did he do? Now, now, תוספות Tosafot by the way
says, רא"ש Rosh tells us here, but I just want to read
you one line. Let's look at the very beginning of תוספות. Tosafot.
He says, ואם תאמר מנימין גר מצרי, v'im tomar Minimin ger Mitzri,
so תוספות Tosafot says, ואם תאמר ולמה לא היה מותר לבוא בקהל?
ולא אין מצרים במקומם? שכבר עלה סנחריב ובלבל כל העולם. v'im tomar
v'lama lo haya mutar lavo be'kahal? Ve'lo ein Mitzrim bimkomam? Shekvar alah
Sancheriv u'bilbel kol ha'olam. I mean, in the days of שלמה Shlomo
they were still the same מצרים. Mitzrayim, But by now we assume
everybody has been displaced.
סנחריב Sancheriv moved whole populations, and the general assumption is, is that
we assume that people are not in their original country. So you
could say maybe this guy didn't come from מצרים, Mitzrim he whatever.
Anyway, he says, ומטעם זה התיר רבי יהושע את יהודה הגר עמוני
umita'am zeh hitir Rabbi Yehoshua es Yehuda ha'Ger Amoni ממסכת ידים, m'masechet
Yadayim, and then he says like this, and then he quotes a
תוספתא Tosefta and he says like this.
Hold on. Now do you see where it says like בקונטרס, bakuntress,
the line that starts with the word קונטרס kuntress about 10 lines
down? Yeah, בקונטרס. bakuntress. Yeah, he says, ובסוטה פירש בקונטרס, דתניא בתוספתא,
שאמר לו רבי עקיבא, ubasota peirash bakuntress, d'tanya b'Tosefta, she'amar lo Rabbi
Akiva, רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva said back to him, מנימין, טעית. Minimin,
ta'isa. מנימין, Minimin, you made a mistake, שכבר עלה סנחריב ובלבל כל
העולם. shekvar alah Sancheriv u'bilbel kol ha'olam. Says, you're thinking that you're
a מצרי, Mitzri, but you're not a מצרי. Mitzri. You know, the
מצרים now, people living now are not the original Egyptians, are not
the original מצרי. Mitzri. So anyway, quite fascinating while the גמרא Gemara
insists that they are the original, not only in שלמה's Shlomo, time,
but even in the time of רבי יהודה, Rabbi Yehuda, תוספות Tosafot
has an extended discussion that in for basically for halachic purposes we
assume that certainly after the period of סנחריב, Sancheriv, post-שלמה, Shlomo but
but already by, you know, mid-end בית ראשון Bayis Rishon time, we
assume that nobody is in their original place. Yes?
Is the תוספתא Tosefta that we have today?
I didn't get a chance to check it. Okay, back to the
גמרא. Gemara.
So is it okay then? So like the—is that what the גמרא
Gemara is saying?
That שלמה Shlomo did not transgress because he wasn't married to them.
That's what I was saying before, that on the one hand the
משנה Mishnah. says that marriage itself is not a problem, you need
to have sex at least for the woman's status to change. That
was by the פצוע דכא. ptzua daka, And here it's saying that
sex itself is not a problem, it needs to also be with
the context with also needs to be marriage.
Do you think there's the whole, you know, the גמרא Gemara? in
סנהדרין Sanhedrin that wanted to eliminate שלמה from עולם הבא? Olam HaBa?
Right? So you know, this is
what can I tell you? Right, exactly. Well, we'll deal with that.
Okay. By the way, though, this is only—this discussion of his about
marriage or sex is about the לא תעשה, lo sasei, the things
that are just simple לא תעשה's, lo sasei you know, the פצוע
דכא, ptzua daka.
the מצרי, Mitzri, עמוני, Amoni, מואבי, Moavi, you know, those types of
cases,
גרושה gerusha to a כהן. Kohein, By the cases of the כרת,
kares, you know, the things about like, like what do you call
it, like the incest cases, that's clearly just about sex. Of course
anyway there can't even be about marriage, marriage isn't even binding in
those cases. Okay anyway, back to the גמרא.
Gemara But marriage wouldn't be binding in these cases?
Yes it would, it's only an איסור לאו, issur lav, at most
it's an איסור לאו. issur lav. Okay, so אמר ליה רבינא לרב
אשי. amar leh Ravina le'Rav Ashi. It said רבינא Ravina to רב
אשי, Rav Ashi, והאנן תנן פצוע דכא וכרות שפכה מותרים בגיורת ומשוחררת.
v'ha'anan tenan ptzua daka v'krut shofcha mutarim bi'giyores u'meshuchreres. So basically the
conclusion so far has been, since it seems that a פצוע דכא
is מותר בנתין, mutar b'nesin, where it seems to be we're going
to argue and similarly therefore
a פצוע דכא כהן Kohein will be מותר בגיורת. mutar bi'giyores. That
seems to be where the גמרא's Gemara going and that's basically how
we פסקן, pasken, believe it or not. So רבינא Ravina said to
רב אשי, Rav Ashi, but didn't we teach פצוע דכא וכרות שפכה
מותרים בגיורת ומשוחררת? ptzua daka v'krut shofcha mutarim bi'giyores u'meshuchreres? That they're
מותר mutar by גיורת ומשוחררת, giyores u'meshuchreres, הא נתינה אסירה. ha nesina
asira. So it only mentions גיורת ומשוחררת giyores u'meshuchreres which are anyway
מותר mutar to a normal Jew. So it doesn't say they're מותר
mutar by a נתין. Netin אמר ליה ולטעמך אימא סיפא, Amar leh
u'l'ta'ameich eima seifa,
ואינו אסורין לבוא בקהל. v'innu asurin lavo be'kahal. לבוא בקהל lavo be'kahal
is to come—is to marry somebody who's in the קהל. הא נתינה
שרי, ha nesina sharei, presumably somebody who's not in the קהל is
permissible. אלא מהא ליכא למשמע מינה. Ella mei'ha leika l'mishma minah. You
can't learn anything from the משנה. mishna. And the basic principle is
that not only for ישראל do we say that if you're in
a category that you're אסור בקהל, assur be'kahal, like פצוע דכא or
ממזר mamzer? etc, you're מותר mutar for those types of people that
are Jewish but אסור assur. for other reasons, like the case of,
you know, נתין and ממזר mamzer and so on, you know, but
also even a כהן. כהן, once he's אסור בקהל, assur b'kahal, actually
becomes מותר, mutar, מותר בגיורת. mutar b'giyorus. Yes.
Were the נתינים still around in the time of the גמרא?
Gemara, I highly doubt it.
Because I haven't heard of anything on the נתינים. They weren't any
in...
Well, yeah, right, the נתינים probably, right, one wonders, it sounds from
the גמרא Gemara that it's not talking about it as a hypothetical
category, it sounds from the גמרא Gemara like it really does have
some group that's identified as נתינים. Okay, let's keep on going. Let
me just actually see if I can read you in two seconds
the הלכה halacha from the שולחן ערוך. Shulchan Aruch.
Here. Here's שולחן ערוך, Shulchan Aruch, סימן ה' סעיף א' siman hei
se'if alef in אבן העזר. Even HaEzer. פצוע דכא וכרות שפכה אסורין
לישא ישראלית ומותרין בגיורת ומשוחררת ואפילו כהן שהוא פצוע דכא מותר לישא
גיורת ומשוחררת לפי שאינו בקדושתו.
ptzua daka u'chrus shofcha asurin
lissa Yisraelit u'mutarin b'giyoret u'meshuchreret v'afillu Kohein she'hu ptzua daka mutar lissa
giyoret u'meshuchreret lefi she'eino bikdushato. Okay, ואפילו נתינה או אחת מספקות מותרת
לו להאי פצוע דכא דלאו בקהל לא גזרו על נתינים ועל ספיקות
אבל אסור בממזרת ודאית שהרי אסורה מן התורה ויש מתירים
אפילו בממזרת.
v'afillu Netina o achat misfeikot mutaret lo l'hai ptzua daka d'lav b'kahal
lo gazru al Netinim v'al sefeikot aval assur b'mamzeret vadait sheharei asura
min
haTorah v'yesh matirim afilu b'mamzeret. So we're
going to learn that a נתין and a ממזר are מותר זה
בזה, mutar zeh b'zeh, right? And a ממזר is also בקהל השם.
bikhal Hashem. So here's an interesting question. Can a פצוע דכא, right,
marry a ממזר? Some even say yes. Some even say yes to
that, right?
And so it makes this huge leap like today the reason why
קדושין kiddushin between a Jew and a non-Jew is not חל chal
is only דרבנן? d'rabbanan?
Well, correct... no. It's not חל דאורייתא. chal d'oraisa. You mean the
reason it's אסור. assur. Yeah. The reason it's אסור. assur So that's
a question. Do you... לא תתחתן בם only בשבעת עממים ba'shivat amamim
or is it about... or is it about all non-Jews? So that
is a question.
אסורי דאורייתא ישראלית assuri d'oraisa Yisraelit say.
Well, right, is it all non-Jews? Exactly. So what is the scope
of the דאורייתא לא תתחתן בם? d'oraisa lo titchaten bam? Right, but
it's not binding דאורייתא d'oraisa because that's just with a non-Jew. Oh,
it's not because of the איסור issur that it's not binding. Okay.
A normal לאו would be binding, like a כהן and a גרושה
gerusha and so on. Next משנה. mishna, Now we're done with פצוע
דכא. עמוני ומואבי אסורים ואיסורן איסור עולם. Amoni u'Moavi asurin v'isuran issur
olam. An Ammonite and a Moabite are forbidden and forever. It's not
like a דור שלישי dor shelishi or a דור עשירי. dor asiri.
גם דור עשירי לא יבוא להם בקהל
השם.
gam dor asiri lo yavo
lahem bikhal Hashem. Right, yeah. Well, we're dealing with... yeah, but the
question is, as we've as we just talked about by the גבעונים
Givonim and the נתינים etcetera and לא תתחתן בם, presumably we mean
even if they convert, they remain אסור to marry, right? That's like
what we just had by the מצרי. Mitzri. Okay, so they can't
marry a Jew. Right. That gets to the קהל השם kahal Hashem
issue, exactly. Just like we talked about by the מצרי. Mitzri. אבל
נקבותיהם מותרות מיד, aval nekivoteihem mutarot miyad, their females are immediately permissible
as soon as they convert. Okay, right. So מצרי ואדומי, Mitzri v'Edomi,
a Mitzri and an Edomite, אינם אסורים אלא עד שלושה דורות. einam
asurin ella ad shelosha dorot. Until three generations, right? דור שלישי יבוא
להם בקהל השם. dor shelishi yavo lahem bikhal Hashem. אחד זכרים ואחד
נקבות. echad zecharim v'echad nekivot. Whether males or females. So the חידוש
chiddush is that even females though are and have to wait three
generations. So it's ironic... right, it's ironic. The עמוני ומואבי Amoni u'Moavi
that are more strict, that are never can marry into a... into
somebody who was a... who was born Jewish or isn't in this
קהל category. Nevertheless, the females are מותר mutar immediately. רבי שמעון מתיר
את הנקבות מיד. Rabbi Shimon matir et hanekivot miyad. Rabbi Shimon says
that מצרי ואדומי Mitzri v'Edomi is just has the same leniency as
עמוני ומואבי, Amoni u'Moavi, that the females are immediately permissible. אמר רבי
שמעון קל וחומר דברים. amar Rabbi Shimon kal vachomer devarim. It's a
קל
וחומר. kal vachomer. ומה אם במקום שאסר את הזכרים איסור עולם, u'ma
im bimkom she'asar et hazecharim issur olam, where the males are forever
forbidden, עמוני ומואבי, Amoni u'Moavi, התיר את הנקבות מיד, hittir et hanekivot
miyad, the females are immediately permissible. מקום שלא אסר את הזכרים אלא
עד שלושה דורות, mekom shelo asar et hazecharim ella ad shelosha dorot,
the place where the males are only forbidden for three generations, the
מצרי ואדומי, Mitzri v'Edomi, אינו דין שנתיר את הנקבות מיד? eino din
shenatir et hanekivot miyad? Certainly we should allow the females immediately.
אמרו לו אם הלכה נקבל, amru lo im halacha nekabbel, they said,
if you have a tradition, we'll accept it. ואם לדין, v'im ledin,
but if you want to argue it, יש תשובה, yesh teshuvah, we
have a response to that. And it doesn't say what the response
is, we'll see in the גמרא, but we don't buy your קל
וחומר. kal vachomer. We'll accept it if it's a tradition, we don't
buy your קל וחומר. kal vachomer. אמר להם לא כי הלכה אני
אומר. amar lahem lo ki halacha ani omer. He said no, I'm
telling you that besides my logical argument, I actually do have a
tradition. Okay, whether in the end they really accepted his tradition, we'll
see. Yes, Amidu.
Is this correct to say, this is a very unusual משנה, with
קל וחומר kal vachomer and a response and...
Right, you do sometimes have מדרש הלכה midrash halacha in it, but
this is not just מדרש הלכה, midrash halacha, there's almost like a
back and forth type of thing.
Yeah, but it is interesting but it is not unheard of. Right.
Okay. מנא הני מילי? mina hanei milei? Where is this from? The
idea that a female Ammonite and Moabite is מותר מיד. mutar miyad.
So אמר רבי יוחנן דאמר קרא, amar Rabbi Yochanan d'amar kra, the
verse says, וכראות שאול את דוד יוצא לקראת הפלשתי...
v'chirot Shaul et David yotze
likrat haplishti... Right, I know, so we're going to basically we're going
to work backwards from דוד, David that רות Ruth must have been
okay. וכראות שאול את דוד יוצא לקראת הפלשתי, v'chirot Shaul et David
yotze likrat haplishti, when שאול Shaul saw דוד David going to confront
the Philistine, Goliath, אמר אל אבנר שר הצבא... amar el Avner sar
hatzava... And Rabbi Yochanan דאמר קרא *d'amar kra* says the verse says
וכהראות שאול Shaul את דוד David יוצא לקראת הפלשתי *u'cheir'os Shaul es
David yozei likras haplishti*. Right, I know. So we're going to basically
work backwards from David, that Ruth must have been okay. וכהראות שאול
Shaul את דוד David יוצא לקראת הפלשתי *u'cheir'os Shaul es David yozei
likras haplishti*, when Saul saw David going to confront the Philistine, Goliath,
אמר אל אבנר Avner שר הצבא *amar el Avner sar hatzava*, he
said to Abner, his general, בן מי זה הנער *ben mi zeh
hana'ar*, the son of who is this child? Whose kid is this?
אבנר Avner ויאמר אבנר Avner חי נפשך המלך אם ידעתי *Avner vayomer
Avner chai nafshacha hamelech im yadati*, he said I don't know. So
Gemara says what? ולא ידע ליה *velo yada leh*, right? I don't
know. That's what it says. God knows if I know, which means
I don't know. ולא ידע ליה *velo yada leh*? What do you
mean? Abner didn't know who David was? והכתיב ויאהבהו מאד ויהי לו
נושא כלים *vehaktiv vayeehavehu me'od vayehi lo nosei keilim*. What do you
mean? He was his armor-bearer. אלא אבוה קמיבעיא ליה *ela avuha kamibaya
leh*. Okay, no.
So what Shaul said is who's his son is this? So he
wanted to know who the father was. ואבוה לא ידע ליה *va'avuha
lo yada leh*? And maybe Abner didn't know the father? But how
could he have not known the father? והכתיב בישי והאיש בימי שאול
Shaul זקן בא באנשים *vehaktiv b'Yishai veha'ish bimei Shaul zaken ba b'anashim*.
The man, meaning Yishai, in the time of Shaul was very old,
he was coming among men. What does that mean? ואמר רב ואיתימא
רבי אבא זה ישי אבי דוד David שנכנס באוכלוסא ויצא באוכלוסא *v'amar
Rav v'isima Rabbi Abba zeh Yishai avi David shenichnas b'uchlusa v'yatza b'uchlusa*.
Whenever he would come in and go out, he would have tens
of thousands of people following him. Okay? So therefore, obviously Abner must
have known who he was. Rashi says that he was the head
over 600,000 for Yishai. So anyway, bottom line is of course Abner
knew who Yishai was. So what does he mean I don't know
who Yishai was? Oh,
I'm sorry, Shaul, thank you, thank you.
Shaul knew who he was. So ויצא באוכלוסא *v'yatza b'uchlusa*. So הכי
קאמר שאול *hachi ka'amar Shaul*.
So this is what Shaul was saying. So why is Shaul asking
Abner? How could it be that Shaul didn't know who he was?
I mean, this is the same David that
was his personal attendant, who carried his armor. I was confusing it
with Abner before. And right, exactly. How could he not know, and
how could he not know who Yishai was? So הכי קאמר שאול
*hachi ka'amar Shaul*. So this is what Shaul was saying. אי מפרץ
אתי אי מזרח אתי *ei mi'Peretz asi ei mi'Zerach asi*. No, no,
no. I know whose son he is. Here's what I'm asking about
him. I want to know what his lineage is. Does he come
from Perez because he's from Yehuda, or does he come from Zerach?
Right, so those are the two strands of Yehuda. אי מפרץ אתי
מלכא הוי *ei mi'Peretz asi malka havei*. If he's coming from Perez,
then I'm concerned because that's an indicator that he's going to be
a king. Why? שהמלך פורץ לעשות דרך ואין מוחים בידו *shehamelech poretz
la'asos derech v'ein mochin b'yado*. Because as we're going to teach a
thousand years from now, a king bursts forth and he makes his
own pathway and nobody can stop him. So Perez means like no
limits, unlimited power and privilege and so on. So therefore that indicates
that he's going to be a king, and then I have to
be jealous of him. ואי מזרח אתי חשיבא בעלמא הוי *v'ei mi'Zerach
asi chashiva b'alma havei*. So Zerach is like shining, that'll be he'll
have some status, but he's not going to be a king.
He's not going to threaten me, exactly.
So מאי טעמא אמר ליה שאול להאי *mai ta'ama amar leh Shaul
lehai*? So
okay, now.
So why was Shaul asking Abner about him? But what was motivating
him, where was he, why was he all of a sudden concerned
that his position was threatened? Because this was
when he was going out to confront Goliath before he actually had
victory. So already the way we're now reading what's going on is
that Shaul's already feeling threatened. What is making him feel threatened already
at this stage? דכתיב וילבש שאול את דוד David מדיו *dichtiv vayalbesh
Shaul es David madav*.
That Shaul clothed David with his clothes.
מדיו כמדתו *madav kemidoso*, that David fit them, it was according to
his measurements. וכתיב בשאול משכמו ומעלה גבוה מכל העם *vechtiv b'Shaul mishichmo
vamala gavoah mikol ha'am*. From his shoulders above, he was higher than
all the nation. So if David was as tall and good-looking as
him and whatever, he felt very much threatened. You know, it's fascinating
because here just by the physical aspects, but you can understand that.
He's handsome, he's tall, he's good-looking, he felt very threatened by him.
So he tells Abner, so yes, David was his attendant, David was
the son of Yishai, he knew all these things, but he wanted
to know does he come from a potentially royal stock or not?
How threatened do I have to be? אמר ליה דואג Doeg האדומי
*amar leh Doeg ha'Edomi*, so Doeg said to him, the Edomite, עד
שאתה משאיל עליו אם הגון הוא למלכות אם לאו *ad she'ata mash'il
alav im hagun hu l'malchus im lav*. You're trying, you're so concerned
whether he's from royal stock or not, I've got a better way
of sort of disqualifying him. שאל Shal. עליו אם ראוי לבוא בקהל
אם לאו *sha'al alav im ra'uy lavo b'kahal im lav*. Maybe he's
not even fit for being a Jew, or fit for marrying, not
fit for being a Jew but fit for just... he doesn't have
even the basic yichus for fit for marrying among the Kahal. מאי
טעמא דקאתי מרות המואביה *mai ta'ama deka'asi me'Rus haMoaviyah*, because he comes
from Ruth the Moabitess. אמר ליה אבנר Avner תנינא עמוני ולא עמונית
מואבי ולא מואבית Amoni velo Amonit, Moavi velo Moavit. *amar leh Avner
tanina Amoni velo Amonis Moavi velo Moavis*.
What do you mean? We've got a braisa that we're going to
teach a thousand years from now that's going to say only the
male and not the female, so that's not a problem. אלא מעתה
*ela me'ata*, so says back to him presumably Doeg, who's Doeg is
the enemy of David, the troublemaker. So Doeg... Oh, you're going to
say that, but then we should say ממזר ולא ממזרת?
So then we should allow even a female ממזר? No, ממזר כתיב
ktiv מומזר. mumzar. That means that there's some problematic blemish because of
their forbidden sex. That's not limited to male or female. So okay,
but he says, so then say מצרי ולא מצרית. Mitzri velo Mitzrit.
Why don't we say the same thing about the Egyptians, right? Which
actually is what רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon says. So I don't know,
he says why didn't you say a פסוק pasuk like רבי שמעון?
Rabbi Shimon? Oh, he says no, שאני הכא דמפרש טעמא דקרא. shani
hacha demafaresh ta'ama dekra. No, here's what entitles us to make this
דרשה drasha of עמוני Amoni ולא עמונית, מואבי Moavi. ולא מואבית. על
אשר לא קדמו אתכם בלחם ובמים, Al asher lo kidmu etchem balechem
uvamayim,
because they didn't come out to you to greet you with bread
and water. That's why not the עמוני and the מואבי. דרכו של
איש לקדם ולא דרכו של אשה לקדם. Darko shel ish lekadem velo
darko shel isha lekadem. That's only something you can hold against the
men. The men are the ones that go out and—it's funny, very
funny, whenever you see the things like, you know, on the movies
or whatever,
somebody comes to the town, it's the women that are coming out
and bringing out the fruit. Oh, but somehow we say the men
should have been the ones to come out, not the women, so
only the men are the ones that are being held responsible. So,
ולא דרכו של אשה לקדם. velo darko shel isha lekadem. הוו להו
לקדומי אנשים לקראת אנשים ונשים לקראת נשים? Havu lehu lekadumei anashim likrat
anashim venashim likrat nashim? So דואג Doeg said, I don't buy that
answer. Let the women come out—men should greet the men and women
should greet the
women. אשתק. Ishtik.
So אבנר Avner was silent. So דואג Doeg now is basically saying,
Saul, you don't have to worry about him. He's disqualified. He's a
descendant from רות המואביה. Rut HaMoavit. So, and אבנר Avner is not
so sure that he is disqualified. ויאמר המלך שאול איתה בן מי
זה
העלם. Vayomer hamelech Shaul atah ben mi zeh ha'alem. So now שאול
says, okay, so go investigate about him. Okay, so now התם by
the way, that's in the פסוקים, psukim, it says it twice, once
when he's going out and another time when he's coming in. So
now the גמרא says, התם קרי ליה נער הכא קרי ליה עלם.
hatam karei leh naar hacha karei leh elem. When he asks the
first time he calls him a נער, naar, here he calls him
an עלם. elem. Now we would say those are interchangeable, but the
גמרא is going to do a cute thing with this. הכי אמר
ליה. Hachi amar leh. This is what שאול says: הלכה נתעלמה ממך.
halacha nitalma mimcha.
So the הלכה halacha is hidden from you. I mean אבנר Avner
didn't know the answer to דואג's Doeg question. אבנר felt pretty confident
that he was okay, but דואג Doeg. asked some pretty good questions.
So שאול is saying this law is hidden from you. צא ושאל
בבית המדרש. Tze ushal beveis hamedrash. Go and ask about him in
the בית המדרש. Beis Hamedrash. At this stage it's not clear to
me if he's talking to אבנר or to דואג. Doeg I think
it sounds like he's talking to אבנר because אבנר was the one
that was משתתק. mishtatek. But we're going to see that when they
get to the בית המדרש, Beis Hamedrash, דואג Doeg is there with
him to create problems. So let's just read one more line. שאל
בבית המדרש. Shal beveis hamedrash.
שאל. So he asked in the בית המדרש. Beis Hamedrash. אמרו ליה
עמוני ולא עמונית מואבי ולא מואבית. Amru leh Amoni velo Amonit Moavi
velo Moavit.
They told him exactly what he had been saying. דוד is not
going to be a problem. אקשי להו דואג. Akshi lehu Doeg. But
דואג Doeg. was there in the בית המדרש Beis Hamedrash and he
challenged everybody. כל הני קושייתא. Kol hanei kushiyata. What do you mean?
I mean, you know, you can't say that because you don't say
it
by מצרי Mitzri and אשתקנהו.
ishtaknehu.
So everybody in the בית המדרש Beis Hamedrash was silenced by דואג.
בעי לאכרוזי עליה. Ba'i le'achruzei aleh. So he wanted to make an
announcement and say, ah, דוד is פסול. No, people are trying to
tell us that he's okay. It's from רות המואביה. Rut HaMoavit. No,
they can't prove their point. דוד is פסול. מיד ועמשא בן איש
ושמו—and Miyad va'Amasa ben ish ushmo you know
what, we'll have to find out how דוד's reputation and lineage was
defended, salvaged, when we come back tomorrow. All right, we will find
out if דוד was really a legitimate king of Israel.
It's a foregone conclusion, I think.
Yeah, you think so?
But not in the בית המדרש Beis Hamedrash at that time.